Guide to the Helen and Newton Harrison Papers M1797
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Helen and Newton Harrison papers
1947-2016
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Harrison, Newton, 1932-
Harrison, Helen Mayer, 1927-
Harrison Studio and Associates
M1797
257.85 Linear Feet 547 containers (273 manuscript boxes, 3 half boxes, 2 cartons, 37 flat boxes, 9 card boxes, 7 audio cassette boxes, 184 map folders; 32 map tubes)
The papers document the life and work of married couple Helen Mayer Harrison and Newton Harrison, leading pioneers of the eco-art movement, whose collaborative career began in the late sixties. Throughout their career, the Harrisons worked with biologists, ecologists, architects, urban planners and other artists, creating works that support biodiversity and community development. The collection contains personal papers; project files pertaining to art projects; correspondence; performance, exhibition, and presentation material; business records; research; interview transcripts; writings; material pertaining to the Harrisons’ time at both the University of California, San Diego and the University of California, Santa Cruz; photographic material; public relations material; audiovisual material; and computer media relating to the Harrisons’ professional career.
Biographical / Historical
Helen Mayer Harrison, born in 1927 in New York City, New York, graduated from Queens College in Flushing, New York, in 1948 with a BA in English. Prior to attending Queens College, Helen matriculated at Cornell University in Ithaca, New York and majored in Psychology (1943-1945). In 1948, she enrolled as a Doctoral Candidate at New York University but later withdrew from the PhD program. Helen received an MA in the Philosophy of Education from NYU in 1952. Helen was enrolled in the Human Behavior PhD program at United States International University (1968-1970) in San Diego, California, but withdrew from the program before the completion of her PhD. Helen studied art and painting in the late 1950s while living in Florence, Italy, with Newton Harrison, as well as additional graduate studies in anthropology, sociology, and social psychology at the New School for Social Research and the University of Pennsylvania and English literature at Brooklyn College.
Prior to becoming a full time artist and professor in the Visual Arts department at the University of California, San Diego, in the early 1970s, Helen held various positions in the field of education. While living in New York state, she worked as a permanent substitute teacher in New York City (1948-1949), a sixth grade English and Social Studies teacher at Mineola Public Schools (1949-1950) a high school English and Social Studies teacher at Newton High School in New York City (1950-1952), and an English teacher at Sewanhaka High School in Floral Park (1952-1953). While living in Florence, Helen was the Director of the International Nursery School (1959-1960). After moving to New Mexico, she worked as an English instructor at the University of New Mexico (1965-1967). Finally, before becoming a full time artist, Helen worked at the University of California, San Diego Extension from 1969 to 1972 as the Program Coordinator and Director of Education Programs. In addition to Helen’s career in education, she was the first New York Coordinator for the Women’s Strike for Peace in 1962. Helen also took time off to raise her four children spending 1953 to 1958 and 1960 to 1965 as a stay at home mother.
Newton Harrison, born in 1932 in Brooklyn, New York, graduated from the Yale University School of Art and Architecture in New Haven, Connecticut, in 1964 with a BFA and from Yale University Graduate School of Fine Arts in 1965 with an MFA. Newton also attended Antioch College (1950-1952) in Yellow Springs, Ohio, and the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts in Philadelphia (1952-1953, 1955-1957), where he received a certificate from the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts and won their traveling fellowship. Newton was drafted into the Korean War and served in the Army (1953-1955).
Newton knew he wanted to be an artist from a young age and immersed himself in art. At 14, he was a sculptor’s apprentice, working after school and during summer breaks. After the Army, Newton completed his studies in Pennsylvania and moved to Florence, Italy, with Helen and their two young children from 1957 to 1960 to study art. After living abroad, the Harrisons returned to the United States and lived in New York City’s lower east side. Newton conducted experimental workshops in painting for children at the University Settlement House, Sloane Neighborhood Center, and St. Augustine’s Chapel (1961-1962). He also taught art to at-risk youth at the Henry Street Settlement House (1962). While in graduate school at Yale University, Newton worked as a Teaching Assistant for an experimental workshop in environmental art and a color workshop (1964-1965). Afterwards, the Harrisons moved to Albuquerque, where Newton worked as an assistant professor at the University of New Mexico from 1965 to 1967. Newton and his family left New Mexico when he cofounded the Visual Arts department at the University of California, San Diego in 1967.
Prior to Newton and Helen’s collaboration, Newton exhibited in a variety of genres, media, and materials typical of many artists in the fifties and sixties. Newton began getting commissions and exhibiting in the mid-1950s. During this period, he made large scale figurative sculptures, cast in plaster, plastic, and bronze. Newton’s “Love Groups” are an example of this type of work. In the late 1950s, Newton moved away from sculpture and began creating field and figure-field relationships paintings. The late 1960s saw Newton working with sculpture again along with various technologically based works. An example of this type of work is the “Artificial Aurora Borealis,” a work comprised of five chambers that emit light. The work was commissioned by the Los Angeles County Museum for the Art and Technology Program and executed at the Jet Propulsion Laboratories in Pasadena, California. This work was a turning point in Newton’s art, as it introduced Newton to physics. The study of physics led him to research biological phenomena, which exposed Newton to ecological concerns. Thereafter, Newton decided to make these issues central to all future work.
At the same time Newton shifted his focus to ecological matters, Helen, a trained social scientist, discovered her lifelong interest in language, narration, storytelling, and the oral tradition aligned with her interest in art. Concepts in the areas of education, philosophy, social sciences, literature, and art coalesced, suggesting to her that the world was in the midst of an ongoing, worsening, but only partly visible social crisis. With this in mind, Helen quit her job at the University of California, San Diego Extension to become a full time artist and professor with her husband at the University of California, San Diego. They are both now retired from University California, San Diego and are currently research professors at University of California, Santa Cruz.
While Helen and Newton arrived at their conclusions through separate study, it was out of the idea of biological crisis that the Harrisons’ first theme was born: survival. Their first collaborative piece, a map charting extinct and endangered species, was part of the Furs and Feathers exhibition at the Crafts Museum in New York City, New York (1971). Afterwards, they decided to take all the resources available to them to make art about survival. Out of this grew the Harrisons’ "Survival Pieces," a multipart work began in 1971 with a focus on farming. For these early works, Newton was in charge of the installation, Helen worked on the performances, and both researched. Over time, the Harrisons’ work mode clarified and both assumed all roles of creating.
The Harrisons’ work explores the relationship between words and images through the use of maps, drawings, paintings, photomurals, and collages with a storytelling/performance component. Ecological concerns, survival, watershed restoration, urban renewal, agriculture, forestry, and other environmental issues remained the focal point of their work over the decades. Their visionary projects have led to governmental policy changes, as well as creating and expanding dialogue around previously unexplored issues, leading to practical implementations throughout the United States and Europe.
The Harrisons have used Ronald Feldman Fine Arts in New York City for their gallery representation since 1974.
Helen and Newton married in 1953 and had four children: Steven, Joshua, Gabriel, and Joy.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was purchased by Stanford University, Special Collections in 2010 and accessioned in 2011, 2012, 2014, 2015, and 2016.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research except restricted material which are closed until the date noted at folder lever. The majority of audiovisual material in the collection has been digitally reformatted and is available to view in the Special Collections Reading Room; audiovisual materials not already reformatted are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy. Born-digital materials are available to view in the Special Collections Reading Room. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Scope and Contents
The papers document the life and work of the married, collaborative team of Helen Mayer Harrison and Newton Harrison, leading pioneers in the eco-art movement. The collection contains a small amount of biographical material and personal correspondence. The bulk of the material documents the Harrisons’ many projects and includes correspondence, designs, financial records, sketches, planning, blueprints, notes, contracts and agreements, schedules, and photographic material. The collection also contains a significant amount of material pertaining to the Harrisons’ performances, exhibitions, and presentations. Also included are business records; Newton’s early work; research; individual files (files kept on colleagues, students, and friends); records documenting the Harrisons’ time at University of California, San Diego and University of California, Santa Cruz; writings; interviews and profiles; and publicity such as posters and fliers announcing conferences, exhibitions, lectures, performances, and workshops. Other formats present in the collection include audiovisual (Series 17) and born-digital material (Series 18), including email. There is also a small amount of Fluxus artwork.
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged into 19 series: Series 1. Personal/Biographical Series, 2. Project Files, Series 3. Project Binders, Series 4. Correspondence, Series 5. Performances and Exhibitions, Series 6. Presentations and Speeches, Series 7. Early Work by Newton Harrison, Series 8. Research, Series 9. Business Records, Series 10. University of California, San Diego, Series 11. University of California, Santa Cruz, Series 12. Writings, Series 13. Individuals, Series 14. Public Relations Material, Series 15. Printed Material, Series 16. Photographic Material, Series 17. Audiovisual Material, Series 18. Computer Media/Born-digital, Series 19. Art and Artifacts
Art, American -- California.; Conceptual art -- United States; Ecology in art; Performance art -- United States.; Pollution in art; Harrison, Newton, 1932-; Harrison, Helen Mayer, 1927-; Harrison, Newton, 1932-; Harrison, Helen Mayer, 1927-; Harrison Studio and Associates
- Series 1. Personal/Biographical, 1947-2008
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the Harrisons’ and their children’s personal papers, as well as biographical material on Helen Mayer Harrison and Newton Harrison. It includes the Harrisons’ articles binders and files, which consists of articles about the Harrisons that the Harrisons and their assistants saved for their CV. The series also has the Harrisons’ CVs, biographies, financial records, and documents about the homes the Harrisons’ owned in San Diego and Santa Cruz, California. Material is arranged by type and then alphabetically.
  - Subseries 1. Article binders, 1957-1989
    This subseries consists of the Harrisons’ article binders, which were created and maintained by the Harrisons and their assistants as a means to document press about the Harrisons and their work. This information was stored in binders and used to update the Harrisons’ CV. This subseries is arranged by the number assigned to the article binders by the archivist.
    - Article binder 1; N. Harrison, #2 thru #72, 1957-1958, 1968-1971, 1979, undated (Box 204, Folder 1)
    - Article binder 2; Newton Harrison, #255 thru #301, 1971, 1973-1980 (Box 204, Folder 2)
    - Article binder 3; Untitled binder, 1978-1983 (Box 204, Folders 3-4)
      Note
      [#151 - #254]
    - Article binder 4; Untitled binder, 1981-1983, undated (Box 204, Folder 5)
      [#1 - #85]
    - Article binder 5; Untitled binder, 1963, 1968, 1970-1989, undated (Box 204, Folder 6, Box 205)
      Unbound
    - Article binder 6; Helen Mayer Harrison, 1972-1983 (Box 205, Folders 4-5)
    - Article binder 7; Helen Mayer Harrison, 1974-1983, undated (Box 205, Folders 6-9)
    - Article binder 8; Articles 1984-1988, Helen and Newton Harrison (Box 206, Folders 1-2)
  - Subseries 2. Article files, 1950-2008
    This subseries consists of the Harrisons’ article files, which were created and maintained by the Harrisons and their assistants as a means to document press about the Harrisons and their work. This information was filed by the Harrisons and their assistants and added to the Harrisons’ CV. This subseries is arranged chronologically.
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, 1950 (Box 206, Folder 3)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, 1960-1967 (Box 206, Folder 4)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, 1968-1969 (Box 206, Folder 5)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, 1970 (Box 206, Folder 6)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, January 1971 (Box 206, Folder 7)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, February 1971 (Box 206, Folder 8)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, March - April 1971 (Box 206, Folder 9)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, May 1971 (Box 206, Folder 10)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, June 1971 (Box 206, Folder 11)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, September 1971 (Box 206, Folder 12)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, October 1971 (Box 206, Folder 13)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, November 1971 (Box 206, Folder 14)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, December 1971 (Box 206, Folder 15)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, December 1971 (Flat-box 271, Folder 1)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, January - April 1971 (Box 206, Folder 16)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, 1972 (Box 206, Folder 17)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, 1973 (Box 206, Folder 18)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, 1974 (Box 207, Folders 1-2)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, January - February 1975 (Box 207, Folder 3)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, March - October 1975 (Box 207, Folder 4)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, December 1975 (Box 207, Folder 5)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, January 1976 (Box 207, Folder 6)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, February 1976 (Box 207, Folder 7)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, March - May 1976 (Box 207, Folder 8)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, September - October 1976 (Box 207, Folder 9)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, November - December 1976 (Box 207, Folder 10)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, December 1976 (Flat-box 271, Folder 2)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, 1976 (Flat-box 271, Folders 3-4)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, January 1977 (Flat-box 271, Folder 5)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, January - July 1977 (Box 207, Folder 11)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, August - December 1977 (Box 207, Folder 12)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, Autumn 1977 (Flat-box 271, Folder 6)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, January - May 1978 (Box 208, Folder 1)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, April 1978 (Flat-box 271, Folder 7)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, June - December 1978 (Box 208, Folder 2)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, September 1978 (Flat-box 271, Folder 8)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, 1979 (Box 208, Folder 3)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, January - June 1980 (Box 208, Folder 4)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, July - December 1980 (Box 208, Folder 5)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, January - May 1981 (Box 208, Folder 6)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, July - November 1981 (Box 208, Folder 7)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, December 1981 (Box 208, Folders 8-9)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, January - April 1982 (Box 208, Folder 10)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, May 1982 (Box 208, Folder 11)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, June - July 1982 (Box 208, Folder 12)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, September - December 1982 (Box 208, Folder 13)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, February - April 1983 (Box 209, Folder 1)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, May 1983 (Box 209, Folder 2)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, June - July 1983 (Box 209, Folder 3)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, August - October 1983 (Box 209, Folder 4)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, November - December 1983 (Box 209, Folder 5)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, February - April 1984 (Box 209, Folder 6)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, May - October 1984 (Box 209, Folder 7)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, November 1984 (Box 209, Folder 8)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, December 1984 (Box 209, Folder 9)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, 1985 (Box 209, Folders 10-11)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, 1986 (Box 209, Folder 12)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, January - August 1987 (Box 209, Folder 13)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, September - November 1987 (Box 209, Folder 14)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, November 1987 (Flat-box 271, Folder 9)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, December 1987 (Box 210, Folder 1)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, 1988 (Box 210, Folder 2)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, January 1989 (Box 210, Folder 3)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, February - March 1989 (Box 210, Folder 4)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, May - October 1989 (Box 210, Folder 5)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, November 1989 (Box 210, Folder 6)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, December 1989 (Box 210, Folder 7)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, April - June 1990 (Box 210, Folder 8)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, July - August 1990 (Box 210, Folder 9)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, September - October 1990 (Box 210, Folder 10)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, December 1990 (Box 210, Folder 11)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, 1991 (Box 210, Folder 12-13)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, 1992 (Box 211, Folders 1-2)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, 1993 (Box 211, Folders 3-4)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, 1994 (Box 211, Folders 5-6)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, January - June 1995 (Box 212, Folder 1)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, October - December 1995 (Box 212, Folder 2)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, January - June 1996 (Box 212, Folder 3)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, August - December 1996 (Box 212, Folder 4)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, 1997 (Box 212, Folder 5)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, 1998 (Box 212, Folder 6)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, 1999 (Box 212, Folders 7-8)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, 2000 (Box 212, Folder 9)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, 2001 (Box 212, Folder 10)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, 2002 (Box 212, Folder 11, Box 213, Folders 1-2)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, 2003 (Box 213, Folder 3)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, December 2004 (Flat-box 272, Folder 1)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, 2004 (Box 213, Folder 4)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, 2005 (Box 213, Folder 5)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, 2006 (Box 213, Folder 6)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, 2007-2008 (Box 213, Folder 7)
    - Article file; Articles and clippings, undated (Box 213, Folders 8-11)
    - Article file; Chapters and essays, 1970 (Box 214, Folder 1)
    - Article file; Chapters and essays, 1980 (Box 214, Folder 2)
    - Article file; Chapters and essays, 1997-1998 (Box 214, Folder 3)
    - Article file; Chapters and essays, 1999 (Box 214, Folder 4)
    - Article file; Chapters and essays, 2005 (Box 214, Folders 5-6)
    - Article file; Chapters and essays, undated (Box 214, Folders 7-10, Box 215, Folder 1-3)
    - Article file; Selected articles and interviews, 1978-1992 (Box 215, Folders 4-5)
    - Article file; Selected articles and interviews, 1978-1994 (Box 215, Folder 6)
    - Article file; Selected articles and interviews, undated (Box 215, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 3. CVs and biographies, 1965-2007
    This subseries consists of the Harrisons’ CVs and biographies, documenting their work together. While there are some CVs and biographies specific to Helen Mayer Harrison and Newton Harrison, the bulk of the material documents their decades long collaboration. This subseries is arranged by type and chronologically.
    - Biographies, undated (Box 215, Folder 8)
    - CVs, 1965 (Box 215, Folder 9)
    - CVs, 1971-1975 (Box 216, Folder 1)
    - CVs, 1975-1978 (Box 216, Folder 2)
    - CVs, 1979-1980 (Box 216, Folder 3)
    - CVs, 1981 (Box 216, Folder 4)
    - CVs, 1982-1983 (Box 216, Folder 5)
    - CVs, 1984 (Box 216, Folder 6)
    - CVs, 1985 (Box 216, Folder 7)
    - CVs, 1986 (Box 217, Folder 1)
    - CVs, 1987 (Box 217, Folders 2-3)
    - CVs, 1988-1989 (Box 217, Folder 4)
    - CVs, 1990-1991 (Box 217, Folder 5)
    - CVs, 1992-1994 (Box 217, Folder 6)
    - CVs, 1996-1997 (Box 217, Folder 7)
    - CVs, 1998 (Box 217, Folder 8)
    - CVs, 1999-2000 (Box 217, Folder 9)
    - CVs, 2001-2002 (Box 217, Folder 10)
    - CVs, 2003 (Box 217, Folder 11)
    - CVs, 2004-2007 (Box 218, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 4. Financial, 1971-2007
    This subseries consists of the Harrisons’ financial records. The bulk of the material documents their invoices, expenses, and loans. This subseries is arranged alphabetically.
    - Financial; Invoices and expenses, 1971-1973 (Box 218, Folder 2)
    - Financial; Invoices and expenses, 2004-2007 (Box 218, Folder 3)
    - Financial; Loans, 1973 (Box 218, Folder 4)
    - Financial; Notes, circa 1973, undated (Box 218, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 5. Harrison family, 1947-2006
    This subseries consists of personal papers belonging to Helen Mayer Harrison and Newton Harrison, as well as their children Gabriel, Joshua, Joy, and Steven. This subseries is arranged alphabetically.
    - Harrison, Gabriel, 1980, 1993, 1997-1998, 2006, undated (Box 218, Folder 6)
    - Harrison, Gabriel [RESTRICTED], 1993 (Box 259, Folder 1)
      Conditions Governing Access
      The materials in this file are restricted until January 1, 2064.